um yeah so i was saying that i i
prepared this
lecture from scratch and
uh it's been challenging
it's the second week i'm not doing
anything but
preparing and reading and studying and
getting crazy but
i think it's a improvement i'm i'm
growing
okay um
ah what do you do research on
how to teach better
uh this week i'll be just reading
everything i could
about this graph neural net graph
convolutional networks
uh i don't know i read maybe a few
tens of publications uh i'm a bit drunk
to be honest
okay so so so so what are we talking
today about
graph convolutional networks exploiting
domain sparsity right
well like yesterday we saw that
also xavier mentioned the three property
of natural signals that are
locality stationarity and
he called it hierarchical well i called
compositionality he used the term
compositionality for
meaning the whole the all three things
but uh
again i guess it's just uh it's just
jurgen
we mean the same thing right um
and so what are these graph
convolutional net networks are again
another type of uh architecture or the
another way of exploiting what is the
structure
of your data right and so let's uh
actually
get it let's get there from just last
week
lesson so last week let's get let's have
a
quick recap right we talk about
self-attention
in self-attention we had this set of
axes right
so x we can go x1 x2 and so on until xt
and they you can you know stack these
x's one after each other you get that
capital x right
matrix uh each small x x
is the size of rn and then my hidden
layer
for the whatever x i take in
consideration
is going to be this linear
linear combination of these vectors in
the set okay
and we know it's actually from i think
lab number four
that a linear combination of vectors can
be written as a
matrix vector multiplication and so we
have here that
the h it can be is equal to this capital
x
or times a right so a contains the
coefficient
that are scaling these vectors okay
then we had like we were saying that all
these coefficients are positive
uh they have to sum to one and then if
only one
is actually one then we have the heart
attention okay and this big
x is just this collection of x's okay
but then again it's a set
right a set means it's not a sequence
there is no order okay
um so so far you should be familiar
right you should be very actually
comfortable with this kind of notation
right
this linear combination of columns it's
just a matrix
multiplication okay so then i was
reading
the literature about this graph
convolutional network and i read and i
read them like
oh it's actually the same thing
what the heck so so so so actually let's
get there from this perspective right
it is my perspective again might be not
the best but
you know you have me so you deal with me
so let's start with this gcn
uh graphic ethnographic graph
convolutional networks
so my a which is this vector uh on the
left
here in the in that in the attention
that is containing all the coefficients
that are basically weighting these
columns
in this case is going to be i'm going to
call this my
agency vector okay and what the heck is
this agency vector
so we have to start introducing a little
bit of notation
in this case i introduce here my first
vertex uh the red one
which is uh also has you know
representing
representing my x uh you know my even x
input and it's gonna have you know my
h uh hidden layer like we were seeing
before
on the on the attention part we had like
this generic
x and generic h so i'm gonna keep using
this kind of generic notation
so i have my generic vertex v where i
can have my
generic x and my generic h okay
and then of course you're going to have
all the other vertices right which i'm
going to be calling them
vj on which you can find the signal
which is going to be the
xj and the hj okay they hit the
representation and the
input value for this specific vertex or
node
and then what well you have many no you
have just the whole
collection of data points
but then there is a difference now we
have that
these uh nodes these vertices are
actually connected
and so we draw a set of arrows
and so right now basically we're going
to have that my capital a my my sorry my
vector a
is going to be having components alpha j
which are equal to 1 whenever there is
an incoming
arrow from vector v j
to myself okay so
if you think about how we were doing
this before for the attention
we were computing a as is of dark max or
just the arc max if it's a hard
version of the attention between uh like
of my
uh scalar product the scalar product of
all those
keys or all those rows times my query
right so you had all the keys times the
query
and then you had this scores now we're
performing soft arg max or
arc max and then you have basically
these values that are
telling you who you should look at
in this case here in the graphical graph
convolutional network
we have this structure that is given to
you
already okay and so again this
agency vector can be thought again as
this vector with
ones corresponding to these
vertices that are having arrows pointing
towards
myself the red guy okay so
if you understand this it's finished the
lesson is concluded
right because exactly everything else
will follow
uh automatically right so
d is going to be my one norm which is
what the number of ones i have right so
if
in my case here d is going to be two
right
what is the size of a in this case in
this case can you tell me
if you're following are you following
answer my question are you hearing me
oh no no yeah and the number of nodes
right so the
number of nodes in this case is six
right and we call this from in this
alpha in the surface tension we were
calling this
lowercase t right and so capita
lower lowercase a a vector is going to
be of course
of size t because you have to multiply t
vectors right so you're going to have t
nodes of t vectors
and therefore you need t coefficients
right so of course
i think a has size t
and d which is the number of ones
basically
is going to be the um
is going to be basically the degree
right i think this can be also written
as the norm
zero i think yeah this is just normal
zero right
cool cool all right um what next
so in self attention we had that my
hidden layer
was this matrix multiplication
of my x times a right so this means the
columns of the x
are scaled by the factor factors inside
a
okay first issue
so if you have multiple ones this h is
going to be larger for
uh vertices that have many incoming
connections right
and if he has like let's say just one
incoming connection is going to be
you know small right so this stuff is
proportional to the number of
uh incoming connections so how can we
fix that
oh hold on messages incoming messages
yeah of course you divide by the number
of items right
and so we multiply that with by d to the
minus one cool cool cool
um so what next or maybe we want to
rotate
things so let's put there a rotating
metrics
um and then we haven't
we haven't considered ourselves right so
this is basically considering all the
incoming edges
but we don't consider ourselves we might
want to consider ourselves right
as there would be a self connection so
we can add this another
another guy right in this ul rotated
version of the x
cool uh then just to make the whole
thing
uh looking like a neural network what do
we add
yeah you know linear function of course
right
relu sigmoid and h whatever okay
uh we said that we have like several of
these vertices right we don't have just
one vertex right we don't just have one
x we have many
of these guys right so we had a set of
vertices or set of inputs right for i
that goes from one to t and this leads
therefore to this matrix notation right
so you just stack multiple h's
you get a matrix by stacking multiple
x's you know you rotate multiple x's you
just get the stack
and then you sum this to the attention
where the attention like the agency
vector now it's going to be agency
matrix
it's going to be all these columns right
uh where
they tell you where where are the
incoming connections right those
incoming arrows
and that d is going to be the uh the
inverse of the diagonal
where you have all the degrees on the
diagonal okay
finish that was it right
graph convolutional networks it looks
like attention to me
but okay so what do we do today for the
lab okay are there questions so far
i mean are you with me are you have you
been following right there is nothing
here that we haven't
seen last time basically well
non-linearities
self-connection where do features come
in
isn't x a feature okay x is a feature
yes
x is a feature and the feature here are
so there is
like there is a graph that is telling
you which
vertices are connected and each vertex
has
a x which is the input and then it's
going to have a
hidden value right
are the previous hidden vectors used to
compute the new one
uh are they they are not right here
you can have multiple layers right and
so the second layer the
h layer next layer is going to be using
the hidden layers like the hidden values
of the previous layer right it's going
to be just a
normal way like you stack multiple of
these blocks right
uh the u the u is just the uh
a term that allows me to consider also
my own value
x okay so right now a is going to
basically give me the
average of these columns that are
incoming
and then u allows me to you know perform
a rotation of my
own self vector so whenever you have
like a graph in this case there are two
options
or it's you and you're like the v the
red v
or is the other which is the vj okay and
so
here you have two terms one is taking
care of the v
red v the other one is taking care of
the v j
final question the agency matrix does
not
have self connections the urgency matrix
has zeros on the diagonal
if you want to consider the agency
metrics with the
ones on the diagonal you can have like
identity plus d a
right okay
so next slide which is going to be the
thing that we are implementing
today okay otherwise did i miss any
question
um so alph is in this a so the diagonal
is
all zeros yeah yeah so agency vectors
the agency vector here has a one only
if the vj which is my neighbor is
actually
connected to me okay and since there is
no a
arrow from myself that goes back into
myself
there is no one in correspondence to
my own position so a agency matrix
has you know in the diagonal all zeros
and then has ones corresponding to the
incoming connections
if you have a non-directed graph then
you have a symmetric
matrix because you don't you have you
know the same one
for both directions it's going to
basically having it's like having a
arrow on both direction of the edge okay
okay got it thank you sure
how is x represented
x is a vector which uh refers to a node
so how do you
represent a node using a vector
how you represent the node uh so x is a
vector right of dimension n
and this is your set of vectors right
this is your set of inputs
you have one to t this is from self
attention
vector self analysis self attention set
right
so this is a set and from this other
slide basically you have that only
some of these axes are connected to
other axes
so you have a set of axes
and then you're gonna have basically a
connectivity
you know specified between these
vertices so x and h
and h next layer and x h next layer and
so on
are basically values in a set
but then the point is that these
elements in this set are connected
through these arrows okay
and so that that's simply it like there
is no magic here
like we were telling you suppose you
have a graph whose
no vote dices are labeled one two three
four five so how do you
convert from label one to x one
but each of these is gonna be just a
number right whatever
and you're gonna just play with this so
you just have to think about
you know this can be thought as a
sequence of again words for a sentence
or can be thought as the pixels in an
image right
it can be just one linear image you know
or you can have you know whatever to a
normal image
so these are just the values the one
that we called
uh in the domain in an rc
right whenever we are mapping the
mapping the
domain capital omega to these image
values
right so this is simply a set
of values and in this case here we just
specify
a specific domain which has connections
between
vertices simple as that
anyhow so we're gonna be checking the
code right now so that you can
understand everything that is going on
okay don't don't don't get too scared
but i don't think there is any more uh
craziness going on uh the only craziness
part is gonna be
the type of graph convolutional network
we are going to be implementing right
now
and so we're going to be starting we're
going to be implementing something cool
because otherwise otherwise would be
boring which is the residual
gated graph convolutional network
with a mouthful and of course it's from
bresson and laurent you can see from the
reference below
so here again we can think about you
know our
own vertex v the red guy which again has
this
input feature x and the hidden
representation
representation h and then you have the
vj now
again with the all representing all the
other
and then you have all these these guys
right
uh in this specific case actually we are
gonna be
uh naming as well the edges so in this
case
my edge has also a
feature on it okay so in this like graph
in this residual gated graph
convolutional network
uh edges also have a representation on
them
and so this is called ej okay and so you
have
all these vertices that were they were
white before now they have like
a color we're going to have an edge
representation for the input layer
x and for the hidden layer right so
we're going to have
e x and then e h
so what are the update equations for
this receivable gated
graph convolutional network so
since it's a residual we're going to
start with our serial connection we have
an
input x the pink one and then we have
class
something right uh something that is
always positive so actually
this could diverge and an easy fix for
this
first equation would be actually having
a additional weight multiplying
the parenthesis right anyhow let's go
for
this version so we have x plus something
for which we take the positive part and
inside we're going to have
my rotation of the input which is
exactly the same
as you were seeing before right so
here we have that
h equal rotation of the
input x right so the same here
we have that h equal okay there is the
received one and then the rotation of
myself
and then we have plus
a rotation of the xj the incoming j
right this rotation it's also scaled
by eta and eta is going to be our gate
so
now you know why it's called residual
gated graph convolutional network
because we have a gate
eta which is based on the representation
living on the
incoming edge ej which is modulating the
amplitude of the rotated
incoming vertex xj
right and finally we're going to be
summing for
all the edges that are coming towards my
own vertex right so for all the edges
that are incoming
i'm going to be rotating the vertex
representation of the incoming
vertex and i'm gonna be then scaling
modulating the amplitude of this
incoming rotated vertex
with this gate right again this gate
it's
a function of the e j so what is e j
let's figure out the equation so we have
e j
is going to be a rotation of my initial
edge representation that is populated
with the input data so
e x is going to be my input data that is
living on the edge and so i rotate that
i sum the rotated representation
of my incoming feature x j
and then i sum as well a rotation of my
own
feature e x right x is my own feature i
rotate it with the matrix e
sweet so this is my e j representation
and then eta is going to be the
following
so it's a sort of similar
like a variant of our soft dark mags
where um we have that the numerator at
the numerator we have the
sigmoid of my ej which is the sum of
these three components at the
on the bottom which is divided by the
summation
of all the sigmoids
of the incoming edges right
so we have a given edge we compute the
usually if you have the soft arc max
you're going to have the exponential
of the specific value divided by the sum
of the exponentials
in this case this gate is given to you
by
the sigmoid of the given edge divided by
the sum of the all incoming edges
right all incoming yeah connections
finally we have that the next layer so
for the hidden layer the next layer
uh edge representation we're gonna have
a residual connection so it's gonna be
my
initial value e x plus the
positive part of this ej again this
may blow up because you're going to be
summing always positive
terms therefore i would suggest
additional weight multiplying these
positive parts such that you know you
can have even negative
values cool cool so
that that's pretty much it right so if
we compare to what we were seeing before
before we had that my hidden
representation
was some non-linear function in this
case we chose the
uh the relu the positive part
right so in this case we have f
is going to be the positive part here
of my rotated representation of myself
plus this term over here which is
so this exad minus one it means take the
average
of the incoming axis right because a was
equal
one for the vertexes that are incoming
towards my own vertex
and then i divide by the d which is the
degree which is the number of incoming
edges right
and so i basically sum all these
incoming values and then i divided by
the number of the incoming values so i
compute the mean
and then i rotate the mean right the
similarly here we're going to do
exactly the same thing we have the
rotation
of all the incoming edges right so these
are all incoming edges
and then i sum them but in this case my
eta is not just a constant that is equal
to one over the number of incoming
connections
but is going to be a number
from zero to one which is weighting my
incoming
vertex representation based on what is
the
representation living on the edge
so there are many
colors and numbers and symbols but i
don't think it's that different from
what we have seen before
the main differences are this gate which
is no longer
a like a constant factor now it's going
to be function of the representation
and then we have this received by
connection again
i would say that here is missing a
additional parameter
right here and here i would suggest to
have an additional an additional matrix
multiplying here
and here such that we can allow for you
know positive and negative values
otherwise
this representation may blow up now how
do we compute the representation for the
second hidden layer so we can call x
hl so it's going to be my layer l
representation and therefore
the x j becomes h l j
and so all we have to do now is going to
be basically saying that my
age at layer l plus 1 is going to be
this current h right but i prefer to use
h and x's in order to remove this
additional
index that may create cows right maybe
chaotic
all right um so i had a question about
if um
in terms of like maybe a potential
example
um i'm not clear what it means to have
this sort of um gated
like recurrent type of
model in the context of graphs
like um so what is an example of
yeah yeah yeah sure so this gating part
here uh the point is that
all these different uh vertices here
they don't have ordering right i don't
know which one is v1 v2
i mean i know the order but this guy
here this red vertex
doesn't know how many neurons sorry how
many vertices are connected to its own
and then it doesn't know how to you know
think about them in different ways
unless there is some information
coming from this edge and so this edge
allows me to basically change you know
modulate
this incoming incoming message
so this guy here is transiting this x
transits down this uh
this line but then it gets modulated
by the representation of by this gate
which is again based on the
representation that lives on that edge
so the edge has a representation
and this eta it gives me a multiplier
basically a factor that
i can use a scalar to multiply
each component of this vector here and
so it allows me to
tune you know what kind of part of the
vector i might be interested in
okay so this is going to be any way
trained with backprop so the network
will figure out
what the heck is interesting what is not
uh
but yeah the rationale here is going to
be basically
given that all the vertices look the
same to me
in this case because you know if you if
you remove this part here
you just get the summation of all these
h's right and this is going to be oh
just let's average
everything well like the thing i told
you here right so this is exactly
what i'm telling you here in this case
here you just have a average
all the vertices will average all the
representation
on the incoming vertices right and so
this is like hey
let's blur out everything can't say
let's let's
let's throw away all the information in
this case instead it's going to be hey
we are not going to be just averaging
out all these incoming
values but we're going to be weighting
them we're going to be
modulating them based on what we think
it might be
relevant or might not so that would be
and is the
um is that superscript l and l plus one
for the h's like does that mean that
this is a graph
structure over time layer layer layer do
you have several layers right in this
network so h so
hl with l equals zero is going to be my
x
it's it's talking about layers and not
like
time yeah there are several layers right
so you have multiple layers
and all of these layers always leave
these layers are still sets right
so as you have like a set of inputs
you have a set of inputs then you have a
set so these are my set of inputs right
then you are going to have a set of
hidden layers a set of second like
hidden layer of the second layer and so
like a second
hidden layers at the second layer and so
on right
and so but in here we just have sets the
only difference is going to be that in
this case
there are sets but then there is also
connections between these elements in
the set
okay and that's the only difference we
have so the only difference between
attention and this stuff here
is that these guys here are given to you
by this agency metrics instead of
being computed with uh attention like
attending and computing the soft
arguments and so on
so this this is my perspective from last
week lesson
so the only step that is the difference
from last week is going to be that
this connection are given to you finish
same everything else is going to be
basically the same
all right so time to go to the notebook
because it's going to be actually taking
forever
unless there are imminent questions all
right so
this was taken it was uh heavily
inspired by the
notebook from xavier but i changed
everything
so yeah i didn't like what he wrote
as in now it's in our format
or in my format so everything is going
to be familiar uh at least for you
when i first read the thing was like
what's going on here
uh okay okay so import uh crap
uh the only difference here we have
these uh import os
which allow me to set an environment
environment variable so this dgl
backhand
set to pi torch allows me to tell dgl to
use pytorch what is dgl
so actually you have to install
ppinstall dgl it's actually in the
environment description
um dji is going to be my library to
use convolutional nets on graphs
very easily so we import this stuff and
also we import this network x it allows
me to
to print a very pretty uh very pretty
charts
okay i set some default oh you can see
now we are using pi torch
so first of all we're gonna be showing
seeing these so this is mini graph
classification data set
it's gonna it's called mini gcd
this mini gc data set i specify the
number of graphs
the minimum number of values vectors on
the maximum number of vectors
no vectors uh vertices right and so
uh here i just call this with the
different names they have
and then i show you here these different
guys okay
so here you have the first type is going
to be the circle type
so the circle graph where you have each
of these are connected to the other one
and see again there is double r alright
then we have the star graph which is
basically everyone connected to the
first body
then we have the wheel graph okay
so you can understand what it means
uh then we have the lollipop lollipop
lollipop
no this is it okay never mind uh anyhow
so it's a cluster of points connected by
a string
it looks like a kite to me but okay
there is the hypercube which is super
cute
which is this crazy guy here um
and then there is this classic green
right so this can be thought as like
an image or whatever right uh
there is a click which is you know fully
connected graph
and then we have this circular ladder
and graph so it's a ladder which is
closing itself right and so what is
going to be our task our task
is going to be given a graph structure
try to classify as being one or the
other right
so each of these graphs are going to be
basically defined by
is this agency matrix and given these
agency metrics we are going to be
basically trying to figure out whether
one graph is
uh one type or the other the point is
that this agency matrix
is going to be of variable size right
because as you
have seen this here before right where
is it
uh you can give a minimum and a maximum
number of nodes and so you can't
really do a straightforward
classification right
okay cool cool um
i didn't say google
okay my google is protesting here all
right so let's add some signal to the
domain right so those are the domain
this is where the
the information stay right so if you
have this guy here where is it
uh if you had this one no this is the
domain and then on top of this you're
gonna have the values the colors if you
have a
color image right so these are the
domains then we're gonna put some signal
on top
so in this case let's actually read
together we can assign
features to nodes and edges of dgl
graphs
the features are represented as
dictionary of of names
strings and tensors call
fields and data and e n data and e data
are syntax sugar to access the features
data of all nodes and edges so in this
case here i'm going to be just telling
that
each of my node information so my x's
are going to be in the degree which is
the basically incoming
number of vertices i have okay
so each node each x has its value on the
number
of the connected guys
each edge instead has the just a num
one so each edge has a number one the
other one has the number of connected
guys
cool uh so here i just generate my
training set and
testing set and then i just plot
these uh to just show you on that these
guys have a feature
both of them are called called feet
right and there is a feet
not like the foot the feet whatever is
pronounced the same
a feet for the node n and a fit for the
e
edge right and so here we go with the
equations for the gated
graph convolutional networks and again
they look terrible because
it's a notebook so we're going to be
using this one right that are a little
bit prettier
all right so before actually reading
uh these instructions let's read
how the the the main let's read the
initialization part of this module okay
so here we can see that we have a few
matrices we have a
b c d and e right so we need those
matrices
and therefore whenever i start my module
which is going to be just a neural
network module from
torch by torch right we're going to be
initializing
uh four uh different matrices so
a b c and d e are n dot linear so
actually in this case there is also the
bias there is not just rotation so these
are
a fine transformations right modules um
moreover we have a batch normalization
for the
hidden representation and basic
normalization for the
for the edges right uh whenever we do
the forward pass we send
basically uh the g the graph
x capital x is going to be the
collection of all these
vertices right so like we have seen in
the attention module
in the attention lesson we had that my
small x
uh we can have like a the set of all
small
x's as represented by the big x right
uh there is no like it's not a syn
sequence it's just a way of
representing a set right so
in this case graphs are made of sets of
vertices
but where i can specify the uh
relationship
now between which vertex is connected to
which
so i have capital x and then capital e x
right which is the
all those edges so we can have like a
set of
uh edges and then we can consider the
matrix where i have all these columns
right
and so here i'm going to be populating
my graph with this representation
on the g n data i'm going to be
defining the variable h which i just
give all my initial representation and
then i'm going to have
ax bx dx and ex
which are going to be the matrix
multiplying
all these columns right so you're going
to get the rotation of all the columns
which are simply obtained by passing the
capital x not the collection of all the
x's to my
matrix a b d and e okay
whereas c c was multiplying
it was rotating just the edge
representation right so we have that
c is multiplying the edge and then we
have
this uh function here that is the the
new function right we don't know about
this stuff
so let's figure out what it is so maybe
now we have to read what's going on here
so in dgl
the message function are expressed as
edge udf user define functions
edge udf user defined functions take in
a single argument edges it has
three members source destination
and data for accessing source node
features
destination node features and edge
features right
so whenever we have this uh edge here
we're gonna have
air presentation living on the edge
then there is a representation living on
the
source vertex right the incoming vertex
i used to call and then we have
ourselves which is the
destination vertex right so we have
source vertex
our edge connecting the source to
destination
and then we have our own destination
vertex
right so you have a representation
living on the source
vertex a representation living on the
edge
and then a representation living on the
destination
and those are x axis if they are
associated to the
first uh layer of my network right are
gonna be called h
if they are associated to the second and
so on layers of my network right
uh so h is my first hidden layer which
is the second layer of a network right
all right so back here uh again so this
uh edge you the user defined function
have a source
that vj destination the just v and the
data leaving on the
on the edge right all right cool
then the reduce function are node
udfs right user defined functions not
the udfs
user defined functions have a single
argument nodes before you had hedge
edges right so the node acts like on a
given node right
so which has two members data
and mailbox so data contains the node
features and mailbox contains
all the incoming messages features
stacked
along the second dimension okay finally
we have that
update all which was
the function we just seen here the new
function
update all has two parameters message
function and reduce
function send messages through all the
edges
and update all nodes optionally apply a
function to update the node features
after receive this is convenient
combination for performing
send from all the edges the message
and then receive for all the nodes
the radios reduce function right so this
is like a
condensed version and so let's figure
out what are
my message function and reduce function
right
so message function we are going to be
first
extracting the bx j
so the the edge is going to be
connecting
my v j to my v and so i'm extracting
here the representation
that lives on v j right so my
bx j is going to be the
bx associated to my vertex j
right so this guy here b x j
cool then i have that my edge
ej is going to be the summation of the
rotated
edge of this edge right
the rotated source right
and then the destination
um vertex right so here you have
so you have the edge representation like
c
rotation c c rotation of e x
right now we have the d of the source so
d x j and then finally e x
for the destination so which is e x
right
cool then i actually store
this ej in this capital e so that we're
going to be ending up with all the
representation for
later usage because later we're going to
be using this ej over here
on the bottom right okay so now we have
computed the message
and therefore so after the message
um after the message is computed we're
gonna be calling the reduce function
and the reduce function finished to
compute the update
formulas right so we have the ax
is going to be the ax for my own data
right so this ax
capital x is going to be all the
vertices and lowercase x is going to be
this one right so
lowercase x then i checked my mailbox
right
so the message function sent a message
through the uh through the edge and
now at the receiving end we get a
message right so
we check the mailbox and we receive this
bx
j right uh so here we got bxj
then i also listen and we have the
representation ej
right so that's coming too then i
compute the sigmoid here i have the
sigmoid for the
incoming edge right so the sigmoid
of the incoming edge and then
all we have to do now is going to be
having that my
h this is going to be my rotated x right
so ax
is the rotated myself the vertex
representation of my own
and then i have to sum right
over all the incoming edges of my gate
which is multiplying my incoming
representation
incoming rotated representation and then
we divide
by all those sigmas right
all those sigmoids sigmoids which is
this one right
so we multiply sigma to this bx
and then we divide by all all of them
right by the sum of a lot of them and
then we sum
uh all these guys right so we have the
summation
of this scaled
bj which is then also normalized by the
sum
of all the sigmas and that's it so we
have now
the lower a h which is gonna be uh
written
in the big uh container of x's h's
and so that's how we uh
write down these three equations right
four questions
well three right we haven't seen this
last one
so what else so now we can retrieve
h right because we have just updated all
the representation
which has been computed here and
returned there
uh then we can also get new the new
edges right because we
we wrote the edge information here right
so here we were writing the new edge
information
and here we've been writing the new x
h information so we retrieve the new h
and the new e we divide by the square
root of the
size such that things don't change with
the
size of the um of the
of the hidden representation this is
just you know technicality but it
allows you to have like uh a consistent
uh scaling factor like we have seen last
week during the
uh set to set not the attention we were
dividing by the square root of the
dimensions such that the
soft arc max was behaving uh similarly
right
regardless of the um of the dimension
right so we don't change the temperature
then we apply a batch normalization such
that we
get nice gradients and doesn't overfit
and you know
all the nice things that batch normal
gives us finally we apply
the nonlinearity right the
h the plus so we compute this
non-linearity for this one and this one
and then we can write that my new h
so the representation for the first
hidden layer so my second layer is going
to be my
input x plus h
right so we have the input x plus this
guy
here this little positive part
and the same we're going to have the e
representation is gonna be my initial
representation
plus this new e finish and we return
h and e uh i have a multiplier
perceptron and then here i have this
stack of layers so here
i just call my gated cn gcn
and so you can see all these matrices
but again we don't care
um some stuff for collecting an accuracy
computation okay let's test the forward
pass so how do we test the forward pass
here i just define my my data and then i
have my batch of x's
is going to be the data that leaves on
the vertices okay so my x
is going to be the data that lists on
the vertices and my e
is going to be the data that lives on
the on the on the edges
these are all ones and these are just
the degree
[Music]
so i i'll show you a few a few of these
values
yes again that
your ease will be quote unquote all once
just for the first
uh first layer or the first step first
uh sorry what's the word
that stack and the rest of them you will
pass the outputs of the previous yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah
absolutely yes so these are the input
values right so my
my graph which is the domain has i i put
something some signal
on at the beginning which is kind of
arbitrary right now
uh for the nodes i put how many input
connections i have
and for the edges i just put one and
then you have several layers of this
uh graph convolutional net uh like
here so you have this gated graph
convolutional net
has a few a few layers right so if you
have l which is the number of layers
you're gonna have as many uh graph
convolutional network layers that are
the one i showed you before
as the numbers you know as as l right
and so you you stuck several of these
layers
and at the beginning you have this
degree and all ones and then
as you have multiple stacks you start
you know having some
representation that evolves right makes
sense right
yes no is would that kind of be like
the value of e would kind of be like the
weight
of the edge sort of is that
right the value on e is the
uh representation right so we e has like
a
he e here uh okay right now it's just
one right but later on in the
in the following up layers this is gonna
have a vector
and this vector basically allow you to
tune this gate
for this incoming message
let's finish the notebook okay otherwise
we don't finish the notebook and then
i can answer every question you have all
right so
i show you here um like this dgl graph
which had these features these features
are going to be my input
i have in this case 133 nodes and 739
edges how how many are what is the
maximum number of edges i can have
you're following
133 square right uh
divided by two yeah
on the order of 133 square right
uh cool all right so let's execute
this one so we see at the beginning the
network
doesn't uh doesn't cannot really
classify this uh cannot classify
correctly and this is just a stupid
thing
so let's actually train now let's
actually figure out how to train this
network
so i have my j my my objective function
which is going to be the cross entropy
of the you know the the scores
the bad scores and the batch labels
right so these are what my network
uh tells me right this is batch scores
the logits
and then i have the the labels those are
the the original
the original labels for the for the
graphs
and then this is actually it ran fine so
we it
everything was working we have the
forward pass
you know loss computation zero graph
backward optimizer step
and so we define here a training
function which is exactly the same as we
have seen all the time
let me run this line as well
so training function we exactly know
everything
right so x's are the data the features
on the
nodes on the vertices e is going to be
the features on the edges
the batch scores the logits are
basically the output of my model
the j the objective function is going to
be the cross entropy between the logics
and the targets then you optimize the
you you clear up the gradients
you compute backwards and then you step
right that's those these are the five
steps
one two three four five steps
finish evaluation the same without the
updating of the parameters
so here we just have the training data
set and the
testing data set and we can check what's
the progress here so far
so here i just show you the uh training
and the testing accuracy
oh sorry let's put 40 epochs maybe
and so let's see whether it works or not
it's getting better
and yep accuracy is starts to
the accuracy starts to grow test
still low okay it's getting up as well
yeah there we go convergence yes yes
so again all we want to think about
right uh if you think about from the
perspective of the
the attention we have a set of values
right and in attention we didn't have
any kind of
connection between these values it's
just a set everything
looks at everyone right so the attention
you have to
check everything that is going on
because you have no idea
which one should be uh looking at what
in this case we okay that's the main
point right
what did xavier said yesterday the main
point
is the sparsity in the agency metrics
right because the sparsity
gives you structure and structure is the
number one
that are telling you who's connected
with whom so if everyone is connected
with everyone
you get everything one right everywhere
uh
see it's converging here so if you have
everyone looking at everyone your agency
metrics is gonna be just
a matrix with all ones um
if you have you know just a few uh
vectors that are connected to each other
then you get you know some uh some
sporadic
ones right so you're gonna get a uh you
know a sparse matrix
okay this stuff was going to 100
accuracy before
i guess i should set a seed such that i
can show you
better better trials um
that was pretty much everything from it
so really there is no much
big deal i think at least from this
first
perspective and what i learned in this
past week about these networks
um are there questions all right i can
take questions right now i mean i didn't
want to
to take forever to finish the class
otherwise
if people have to leave they can't it's
also i am nine minutes over so i'm
also not on time but you know
better than worse
yes so what exactly did we
predict here yeah no we had the classes
the seven classes of graphs in the
beginning um
so so what are the classes
these are the classes and then i'm going
to be generating
down here i'm generating my
uh where is the training data set
i can't see how long train train train
[Music]
here so training data set it creates um
this data set of 350 graphs
that have anything between 10 to 20
vertices each and then
they can be anything uh
of those eight classes we have seen
before okay
it can be uh anything like let me
zoom here so it can be class seven six
five four three two and one okay
and zero so you can have any of these
one and now
now you're asking this this stuff has a
variable number of vertices right
and now you're asking your question in
your uh
your network which net which type of
graph did i give you
right and so our convolutional
graph convolutional network tells you
which type of graph
you're looking at right so it's doing
basically a classification of your
urgency metrics right which is
specifying the connectivity
of these vertices
so about the so the train set is a set
of
small graphs right
and the batch size there is 50 so that's
graphs of varying sizes varying number
of nodes from 10 to 20
yes it's not necessary that each batch
should have
graphs with the same number of nodes uh
that's what's done inside
that's what was it was done in terms of
uh from dgl
for for giving you you know uh speed in
in training right so but that's that's
that's that's done uh behind the
behind your back right uh it's the same
as you when you train for language model
right so you want to
batch all the sentences with similar
lengths such that you don't waste
computation so it's the similar way in a
similar way you can do here as well
right
but what did the what was the dimensions
of the output
look like um here
so my
yeah so my here i have an mrp
that goes from hidden hidden dimension
of the whatever thing
to my output dimension so what is the
output dimension
let's go figure out out the output
dimension number eight
right so eight are the possible classes
therefore i will give you eight you know
eight vector
a logic of dimension eight uh finally
whenever you have this
logic of dimension eight so it's just a
classifier right
you plug these inside the cross entropy
uh
here loss of my logics against my
labels and this loss is defined
down here is my cross entropy which
expects logics
and then computes you know the final
score
and then you just run back propagation
so did every node
have a like a logit
um and the label each node
has the same label which corresponds to
the class of the overall graph or is
that not how that works
each graph has a
vector of logics right so you want to
classify
graphs different graphs so you provide
these graphs
to the network and these graphs have
arbitrary structure
right they don't have a finite number of
vertices
so you have you know let's say you have
like
10 graphs uh and each of them are like
you have
a graph of size 5 size 10
size 15 size 20. so you have sets
with different number of vertices and a
specific connection between these
vertices
so given these variable length
sets you have to specif and you specify
you you tell the connection between
these vertices
you ask your network to tell you give me
a
logit vector where you're going to be
showing me
basically what graph this belongs to
right which family it belongs to
so 8 eight are the possibilities you
have you know circle star blah blah blah
each input that input graph will be
mapped
towards one specific of this guy right
so you just do
a classification of the type of graph
but the point is that
this graph have a variable number of
vertices okay
so you have to basically uh uh
query somehow the the the structure
right the
graph convolutional net has to
intrinsically
extract what is the typology
of connectivity you
provide okay
cool thank you we are using this example
that was shown was classification of
graphs
yeah but also they can be a use care
mostly there would be a use case in real
world where we have one single
graph where each node represents a
particular entity
and we need to classify those entities
so then how do we
do that like take some part of a graph
and drain the model over that
and then redress so so so okay this one
here you get
uh you have like different graphs and
then at the end you're gonna be
getting them all together right so
whenever you have the
uh gated cnn here you at the end
you you have like forward you get this
uh gc this part here right and you have
mean nodes right so
dgl y you get the mean of
all the nodes and then you apply the mlp
on this mean representation uh this is
for
this classification of the whole graph
right
uh but then if you'd like to do the
other stuff right which is gonna be
you you don't have this function right
you just don't have this line
and you're gonna be applying like a a
vector like a logic vector
like out of each vector right so each
vertice
each vertice you're gonna have a logic
a logic for like a vector logic for each
vertex
a vertex vertex right
it's called yes yeah okay cool so you
have a logic per vertex and then you do
the
uh training on each of these guys right
and so that would be the um for example
if
there is a if you go to dgl
d dgl.ai
this class took really a lot of effort
guys
tutorial uh this one
tutorial now what is it
there is a come on
okay here
yeah cool so in this case they are doing
um they are doing
classification of the nodes okay this is
the second
type of thing so in this case you have a
karate karate club i'm not sure if
you're familiar
and there is like the instructor number
zero and then there is the
uh the manager number three 33.
and then these edges represent uh
what are the um basically the
uh interaction outside the club right in
in real life right so number four
you know interacts a lot with the
instructor outside the club
and number 26 interacts a lot with
number with the
manager outside the club so you only
have two labels you have instructor and
manager and now you'd like to get a
label for
all these other nodes all these are the
vertices
so whenever you do the training part
this is called semi supervised learning
because you only have a few labels right
so whenever you
train this stuff you're going to have
you know okay you have your comp net not
your graph content
which is outputting a number of classes
for each
vertex right so each vertex has the the
full logic
but then during training you have here
that
the the training is going to be the uh
you get the logic
these are logics for every vertex but
then when you
compute the final loss which is the
negative log likelihood
you only select the
labels that you have which is label for
the 33 and the
what are the two guys right where so you
have 0
and 33. these are the only two uh labels
you have
and so there is a vector which is called
0 into 33
33 somewhere yeah here this is my label
nodes they are just these two guys
and so in my uh training laws here
you only select the two nodes that are
that have a label you enforce those
variables to be this one right
and then you train classical stuff right
of zero grad
backprop optimize step and these allow
you to
basically propagate through out the
whole
network structure the whole graph
structure what is this information that
has to come out from the logics of two
specific vertices right
so you have several layers stack of
convolutional
graph convolutional nets and then you
enforce
you know those two vertices to output
that specific label
uh and then you backprop and then
basically all this
information propagates through network
which
propagates a kind of representation
across this
domain and it shows you
if you do a plotting uh this is at the
beginning so this is the representation
or of the vertices um without training
and then after you train after a few
epochs you can see
how this representation gets attracted
right
so 0 and 33 gets pulled away such that
they are
linearly classified
uh when they are you know easy
told apart and then these are basically
dragging
uh vertices close to them based on
basically on the number of connections
they have sort of right
and that's how you do uh classification
on
on vertices rather than classification
of
graphs right maybe yeah yesterday we
didn't quite mention
how you apply uh these things but again
like xavier like myself
are not maybe too interested in the um
application part but perhaps more in the
in the algorithmic part
did i answer your question oh that makes
sense yeah okay awesome
at least i make sense sometimes
more questions
no you're done you're fed up
everybody else left huh there are 18
people
yeah dinner i'm hungry my roommate just
ate my dinner like
the hell these two weeks were crazy
i really worked a lot all right
peace bye-bye
all right so this was like i think
one of my most intensive lectures so far
um i prepared like in
under one week and i think i may have
covered
a lot of materials so it's totally
reasonable to be like somehow
overwhelmed at the moment but then how
can you actually
squeeze out everything out of this video
right so there are a few steps
i would highly recommend you to follow
starting with
you know comprehensions issues right
again
i might have been confusing i have also
re-recorded
a few new chunks because i messed up in
class
so if you have any question i have not
yet addressed
just type it down in the comment section
below this video
moreover if you'd like to follow up with
me on the latest news about
teaching and machine learning and very
cute and pretty things
just follow me on twitter i will you
know
talk about the latest news over there
moreover if you'd like to be always up
to date with
my latest content i would recommend you
to subscribe to my channel
and click on the notification bell such
that you don't miss any
new video if you like this video
you know don't forget to press the like
button
i really appreciate that
searching so each of these videos have a
english transcription we have a japanese
spanish italian turkish mandarin korean
translations as well available for you
if english is not your
primary language and again if you'd like
to help out in the translation
process please feel free to contact me
by email or on twitter moreover
you should really really really take the
time to go over
the notebook we have covered today
uh and check every line of code right so
because there are many things
i may have you know not have spent
enough time today
just for sake of you know keeping this
video
under a within a specific time amount
but then you should really go through
every line and deeply understand what's
going on and if you find
a typo or error a bug like many of you
have already found
do please report it on github and if you
feel
inclined just you can also send a pull
request by fixing this error okay
that's great because we can you know all
benefit from your contribution and you
also get some value
out of you know getting your hands dirty
right with the code
and finally you're going to be helping
me and the whole machine
deep learning community that are using
this material
and that was pretty much it thanks again
for sticking with me
and as i've been told to say like share
and subscribe
see you next time bye bye